Start a new פרק, perek, מזל טוב mazal tov everybody, and we
are doing כל הבשר. Kol Habasar. We will be on this for
about three weeks and this entire פרק perek is devoted to בשר
בחלב basar bechalav
and so we're going to be doing a lot of practical הלכה.
halakha. So we start at the bottom of ק"ג עמוד ב', kuf
gimmel amud bet, we have a דף daf to catch up on
and three lines from the bottom it's a new פרק. perek. כל
הבשר אסור לבשל בחלב חוץ מבשר דגים וחגבים. Kol habasar assur levashel
bechalav chutz mibasar dagim vechagavim. You can't cook any meat with milk
with the exception of the meat of fishes and grasshoppers.
Is there an exception there or no?
No. On the top meat and grasshoppers. ואסור להעלות עם הגבינה על
השולחן חוץ מבשר דגים וחגבים. Ve'assur le'haalos im hagevinah al hashulchan chutz
mibasar dagim vechagavim. And you can't have together with cheese on the
table meaning if it's even rabbinically prohibited with the exception of
meat of fish and grasshoppers. Not only is it you can't cook
them together which is the biblical, you can't have them on the
same table implying that you, right, and we'll see a later משנה
mishna about that that you can't have meat and milk or meat
and cheese on the same table. And again with the exceptions of
fish and grasshoppers which the fact that we're extending even these rabbinic
prohibitions to it is a point that the גמרא Gemara will pick
up on in a minute. And then it says הנודר
מן הבשר hanoder min habasar at an unrelated point to the question
about meat and milk but a question about the definition of meat.
If somebody takes a vow that I won't eat any meat, actually
that's not the vow that would be a שבועה, shevua, basically says
all meat in the world is forbidden to me, makes a נדר,
neder, then מותר בבשר דגים וחגבים. muttar bebasar dagim vechagavim. They are
permitted to eat the meat of fish and grasshoppers so even in
the world of vows it is not considered to be meat. And
now vows normally go by the vernacular so it just points out
that people normally when they say meat, what do we have for
tonight's dinner, meat, nobody is expecting to get fish, so therefore certainly
not grasshoppers you're not expecting. So even in the vernacular they're not
considered to be meat and that relates to the world of vows.
Now this also might be hinting towards why at the rabbinic level
we extend the prohibition to things like birds. For the most part
we will see in a minute the גמרא's Gemara discussion about this,
we generally assume that birds are not included in the Bible's prohibition
in the תורה's Torah prohibition of meat and milk for the simple
reason that birds don't have mother's milk. You shall not cook a
kid goat in its mother's milk, birds don't have mother's milk. So
it's pretty universally accepted although there is a debate in the תנאים
Tannaim about that that birds are not included. Why then are they
included rabbinically? And one of the reasons might be because they are
what we would normally consider to be meat. And since we think
about this much less in terms of the biblical verse of a
kid goat in its mother's milk and much more in the terms
of בשר בחלב, basar bechalav, meat and milk, so we naturally therefore
will instinct that the chicken meat is included. If you actually tell
somebody, oh by the way
chicken and milk together is not really biblical it's only rabbinic, some
people won't believe you, right? What do you mean? It's meat and
milk because we don't think in terms of the biblical verse we
think in terms of meat and milk. So that could be the
last line of this משנה mishna which talks about the vows which
is the world of the vernacular and common perception might implicitly inform
the first line of the משנה mishna about why it extends to
the prohibition why the prohibition extends even to fowl because of our
natural way of including fowl in the category of meat.
Yes maybe you're addressing the will I mean to me the whole
concept of not eating milk and meat at the same time is
a far stretch anyway I mean maybe we'll get there.
We will get there. Okay but right yeah yeah we'll get there.
So there's two questions, one is the degree to which we rabbinically
prohibit certain actions which are not prohibited in the תורה, Torah, not
just cooking them together or eating them cooked together but eating them
side by side or even having them on the same table. That's
one area of rabbinic extension. Then there's the other area of rabbinic
extension which are not just the things that the תורה Torah prohibited
and even including things like birds. Okay so we'll get to both
of those but I do want to point out that the משנה
mishna by putting these two things together I think might even be
suggesting why it is rabbinically extended to birds. I would also point
out that if you remember until now all the משניות mishnayot leading
up to this, אותו ואת בנו, Oto Ve'es Beno, כיסוי הדם, Kisuy
Hadam, גיד הנשה, Gid Hanasheh, had a very particular structure. It applies
whether it's חולין Chullin or מוקדשין, Mukdashin, non-sacrifice or sacrifice, in ישראל
Yisrael or out of
ישראל, Yisrael, in the presence of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, not
in the presence of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it dropped that
structure and it's going to resume it actually coming up by like
שילוח הקן Shiluach Haken and so on. So it's a little funny
that it drops it here. It's in the תוספתא. Tosefta. תוספות Tosafot
doesn't really know why it dropped it but it seems here that
the משנה mishna maybe has bigger fish to fry, excuse whatever,
bigger yeah it's trying to say there it's just like a little
checklist oh it applies to קרבנות korbanos doesn't apply to קרבנות korbanos
here really doesn't. Yes, yeah, we're going to, that's coming right up.
So let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. One more.
Yes, I was just ready. I noticed that רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says כמותר לאכול
בשר basar אחר גבינה *kmutar l'echol basar achar gevina*. Yes, see, is
that custom that dates from after רש"י Rashi
*Rashi*?
What? We're going to get to all that in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. Okay, so about eating meat after milk, milk after meat, all
that, and add to cheese, is that your question? Oh, you mean,
oh, you mean the hard cheese question? That's your question?
Yeah, because רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says כמותר לאכול בשר אחר גבינה *kmutar
l'echol basar achar gevina*. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So when's that? That's מהר"ם
מרוטנבורג *Maharam of Rothenburg*, 13th century. Yes. Yeah, after רש"י Rashi *Rashi*.
Yes. Okay. רש"י Rashi *Rashi*,
11th century. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says העוף אסור מדאורייתא *Haof assur
mi-d'Oraisa*, implies that fowl is biblically prohibited. Now, why is that? I
just gave a whole פירוש *perush* about it's the vernacular and our
conception and that's why we extended it. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says
the reason it assumes this is not just that the משנה Mishnah,
*Mishna* didn't distinguish, but also that the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* extends the
rabbinic rabbinic safeguards to all meat, right? We know that not only
can't you cook them together or eat them cooked together, you can't
eat them even as we're going to see, cold together, you can't
even, as we're going to see, have them on the same table.
And so why are we making all of these rabbinic extensions? And
at least maybe we could understand that we would make these rabbinic
safeguards if there was a biblical concern. But it's hard to understand
that we would make all these safeguards if it was only a
rabbinic issue. So the fact that we don't even allow it on
the table together with cheese suggests that at least we're dealing with
a biblical concern at the back, you know, that stands, you know,
ultimately on the, you know, in the background. So therefore the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* assumes that the problem here has to be biblical. And
therefore it extends even to, so it says, it sounds like that
the prohibition of is even about, the fowl, the birds, are even
biblically prohibited. So כמאן k'man? *k'man*, who is that going like? דלא
כרבי עקיבא *d'lo k'Rabbi Akiva*, not רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*.
דהא אמר *ha amar* he says in a later משנה Mishnah *Mishna*:
חיה ועוף אינם מן התורה *chaya v'of einam min ha-Torah*. Not only
birds, but also wild animals, like deer and so on, are not
biblically prohibited. Only things that are like the גדי *g'di*, that are
like the kid goat. Okay, and that pretty much is like almost,
you know, it's certainly the exclusion of birds is almost universal. All
right, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here attributes it to רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*, but it's pretty universal. So here it sounds like
birds are biblical because of these safeguards. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
אימא סיפא *eima seifa*, let's look at the end of the משנה
Mishnah *Mishna*: הנודר מן הבשר מותר בבשר דגים וחגבים *ha-noder min ha-basar
mutar b'vasar dagim v'chagavim*. It says if somebody takes a vow against
meat, you can eat fish and grasshoppers. העוף אסור *ha-of assur*, which
suggests that or is pretty clear that birds are prohibited; they're included
in your vow. אסור לרבי עקיבא *assur l'Rabbi Akiva*. Now that goes
to a different רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*. רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva. *Rabbi Akiva* we know from נדרים Nedarim *Nedarim*. What does רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's *Rabbi Akiva* say in נדרים *Nedarim* by vows? He
says דאמר כל מילי דמימלא עליה שליח shaliach בר מיניה הוא *d'amar
kol mili d'mimla alei shliach bar minei hu*. Anything that a messenger
has to check in about is included in a category. What does
this mean? Let's take a look. It's very clear. דתניא *d'tanya*, we
taught in a ברייתא braisa, *Baraita*, or דתנן *d'tnan* really, it's a
משנה Mishnah *Mishna*: הנודר מן הירק *ha-noder min ha-yarak*, somebody takes a
vow against and prohibits on himself all types of vegetables. מותר בדלועין
*mutar b'dilu'in*, you can eat gourds. Gourds are not considered normal vegetables.
Meaning this is not again a scientific, you know, question about categories.
This is a question about how people refer to it. By the
way, it's actually talking about vegetables, so of course we all know
that tomatoes are fruits, right? So if you prohibit yourself against vegetables,
would tomatoes be prohibited? And the answer would be yes, because everybody
thinks about tomatoes as vegetables even though they're fruits. Actually I remember
once reading that there was a once a, a serious import tax
against vegetables. I think that's how it worked.
And somebody was importing tomatoes and trying to argue that they were
a fruit and not a vegetable and that they were, and that
they were exempt from the tax. And the Supreme Court ruled when
it comes to דינים *dinim* of the of the Congress, הולך אחר
לשון בני אדם *holech achar lashon bnei adam*. And they ruled that
tomatoes were considered vegetables. So anyway, the same is true by vows.
We go by how people refer to it. Now, if I, so,
so the first opinion is gourds are not what people call vegetables.
And so they're not included. What? They're fruits. Gourds are fruits. Just
goes to show I don't even know. Why? Because they have their
seeds inside. Okay, that's, oh, okay, because when you scoop out like
a thing like a, what do you call? Like an acorn squash,
right? Oh, okay. Just like tomatoes. Okay, good, so it's consistent. All
right. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אוסר *Rabbi Akiva oser*. But רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva? *Rabbi Akiva* prohibits. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* says
gourds are included. אמרו לו לרבי עקיבא *amru lo l'Rabbi Akiva*, they
said to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*: How can you say
gourds are included? והלא אמר אדם לשלוחו קח לנו ירק *v'halo omer
adam l'shlucho kach lanu yarak*, a person tells his messenger: Go get
for us some vegetables. והוא אומר *v'hu omer*, and he'll come back
and say: לא מצאתי אלא ela, דלועין *lo matzati ela d'lu'in*, I
only found gourds. So you see, he doesn't assume that it's included
in vegetables because he'll say I didn't find vegetables, I only got,
there were only gourds on the market. אמר להם *amar lahem*, so
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Rabbi Akiva* said back to them: כן הדבר
*kein ha-davar*, that's exactly my point. כלום אומר לא מצאתי אלא ela,
קטניות *klum omer lo matzati ela kitniyos*? He doesn't say I didn't
find vegetables. or I found rice. אלא Ella, why does he mention
gourds? שדלועין בכלל ירק shedelu'in bichlal yerek because they are in the
category, they may not be the sort of prime example of vegetables
but people include them as at least sort of peripheral vegetables. Okay?
ואין קטנית בכלל ירק ve'ein kitnis bichlal yerek but you know things
like lentils or whatever are certainly not included. I keep on saying
lentils, it's what's the word, legumes, excuse me. Legumes are certainly not
included in vegetables. So this is a category. What do you do
about the thing that is certainly not obviously outside, not obviously inside
and somebody double checks and say oh I couldn't find the prime
example but do you want this? Which so now that puts this
in some gray zone, not necessarily clearly included or excluded. So רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that would be included in the vow. Now
there's actually a question whether he means it would definitely be included,
would you get lashes for it, would it be biblically included. But
at some level the fact that you have to check in about
it means that it's enough in the periphery that it's included in
the vow. So our משנה, Mishnah the גמרא Gemara assumes that that
the same is true with our with fowl, with chicken. If you
say go get us some meat for dinner, okay, the גמרא Gemara
assumes and the person well I couldn't find any meat but they
had some nice chicken on sale. Now I think most of I
don't know but maybe most of us would assume that you wouldn't
even have to check with that but the גמרא Gemara assumes that
you had to check at least בשר for them meant בשר בהמה
basar behema and therefore the fact that you are checking for רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would be included for the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
not. So the fact that our משנה Mishnah says that chicken is
included says that at least we're going like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
from this issue about vows. So in the beginning then how it's
not going like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva The beginning implies that birds
are biblically prohibited from meat and milk and that's not רבי Rebbi
עקיבא position so it's inconsistent. Is this רבי Rebbi, עקיבא or not
רבי Rebbi, עקיבא? By the way I should mention interestingly enough that
the גמרא Gemara in נדרים actually says that according to רבי Rebbi
עקיבא under most circumstances even fish would be included. If you say
get meat you might say I didn't find meat but I found
a nice salmon you know steak or whatever you know that might
also be included. So actually it doesn't even work perfectly to רבי
Rebbi עקיבא because here we're including chicken but we're not including fish.
So the גמרא Gemara gives a special circumstances in which you know
the person didn't want fish. Okay but anyway we're saying the end
which includes chicken with something that you would check about if somebody
had asked for meat is רבי עקיבא, the beginning that includes chicken
in בשר בחלב basar bechalav is not רבי עקיבא because רבי עקיבא
says it has to be just like the kid goat. Yes.
So this might be sort my rabbi insists you're supposed to eat
meat on שבת Shabbat and יום טוב Yom Tov but he says
fish suffices. Aha.
Well that's a different conversation. The reason but even meat has to
do with the issue on the one hand you the primary purpose
of eating meat on יום טוב Yom Tov at least is because
of the meat of קרבנות. korbanos.
Yeah and we never
and we don't have right and we don't have that but on
the other hand nowadays that we don't have the meat of קרבנות
korbanos it's more about just pleasure and enjoyment and that's why some
people don't feel you have to eat meat at all if you
don't want. And there are a lot of rabbis who say on
שבועות Shavuot etcetera exactly yeah.
So I just want to understand so he's saying קטנית kitnis is
not a vegetable, no one would even think of that as? Exactly.
Even though today we would.
Right, but in the vernacular. So anyway how you deal with it.
So the
גמרא Gemara says רישא רבנן וסיפא רבי עקיבא. reisha rabanan vesifa Rabbi
Akiva. How could the beginning be the Rabbis who would include birds
in the prohibition of meat and milk and the end רבי עקיבא
who says that birds are included in the definition of meat for
vows? So אמר רב יוסף amar Rav Yosef so said רב יוסף
Rav Yosef רבי היא. Rebbi hi. It's רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda
Hanasi, he's free to pick who he wants and which opinions he
likes. These are really conceptually unrelated
opinion. ונסב לה אליבא דתנאי. venasav lah aliba detana'ei. He goes, he
picks his תנאים, Tannaim, בנדרים סבר לה כרבי עקיבא. bindarim savar lah
keRabbi Akiva. When it comes to vows he holds like רבי עקיבא
that says if a שליח has to check in, it's included at
least in the periphery of that term in the vernacular and therefore
it's included in the vow. בבשר בחלב סבר לה כרבנן. bevasar bechalav
savar lah kerabanan. And by meat and milk he holds like the
Rabbis that say that it is biblical. Now you have to realize
by the way the idea that there are the Rabbis out there
that hold that meat that birds are biblical for meat and milk
is very questionable. There really the name the תנאים Tannaim that we
are going to see in a משנה Mishna. later on do not
include birds. Okay? And birds is if anything you know almost by
definition have to be excluded. They how do you fit birds into
a verse that speaks about mother's milk? Okay? So unless you really
abstract and genericize the verse to say oh meat means meat and
milk. Okay? But to some degree it has to be built after
the model of goat in mother's milk. Birds can't be in there.
The גמרא Gemara. is essentially making an opposing opinion by claiming that
our משנה Mishna says it's biblical and that is the Rabbis, that's
an opinion that argues with all the תנאים Tannaim we're going to
see later that exclude birds. This משנה Mishnah by including birds is
implicitly saying that it's biblical. Now again the משנה Mishnah never said
biblical but again תוספות Tosafot says because of the safeguards that are
in the משנה Mishnah it suggests that it's biblical so from that
we are creating this opinion that birds that there's an opinion out
there that birds are biblically prohibited. But now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
the רבנן rabanan *Rabbanan*, or the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma *Tana Kamma*
of this משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* that we are understanding means this line
biblically. One minute, let's just see now the final answer the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*, which gets to this point. אמר רב אשי Rav Ashi.
*Amar Rav Ashi*, רב אשי *Rav Ashi* says no, כולה רבי עקיבא
היא *kula Rabbi Akiva hi*, it's all רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, והכי
קאמר *vehachi ka'amar*, this is how the משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* reads: כל
הבשר אסור לבשל בחלב מהם מדברי תורה מהם מדברי סופרים *kol habasar
asur levashel bechalav mehem midivrei Torah mehem midivrei sofrim*, all meat is
prohibited to cook with milk, some biblically, some rabbinically. Yes, all meat
is prohibited, but it's not all biblical. Some is rabbinic. The birds
are rabbinic. Okay, חוץ מבשר דגים וחגבים *chutz mibasar dagim vechagavim*, except
for fish and grasshoppers, שאינם לא מדברי תורה ולא מדברי סופרים *she'einam
lo midivrei Torah velo midivrei sofrim* are neither biblical nor rabbinic. So
yes, all is prohibited, but it's not all biblical. Now, what I've
been telling you is part of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s question was
not just that they're all mentioned in the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, but
that it even makes all of these safeguards about having them at
the table at the same time. Would we really do that for
something that's just rabbinic? So that's exactly the next question the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* asks: if it really is just rabbinic, the birds, how
come we have all of these safeguards? You had a question, Charlie?
Yeah, so is there a תוספתא *Tosefta* or a ברייתא baraita *Braita*
somewhere
that has birds according to a תנא *Tana*? I'd have... I can
double-check, but I don't think so. If so, it's very rare. You
know, the idea that birds are included is very strange and the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is right, and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is trying
to attribute it to this משנה Mishna *Mishna*. The only way you
can get it is you say the פסוק *pasuk* is just an
example but it's... but you know, you abstract it to the point
of meat and milk. That doesn't have to really pattern itself after
the פסוק *pasuk* at all. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
saying if it really is rabbinic, let's understand how we'd make all
these safeguards. ואסור להעלות *ve'asur leha'alot*, you can't even have it at
the table together with cheese and now we're saying even birds that
are rabbinic. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמר רב יוסף *amar
Rav Yosef*, so said רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*, שמע מינה בשר עוף
בחלב דאורייתא de-oraita *shma mina basar of bechalav de'oraisa*. No, from this
I can tell you that it is biblical, birds, you know, a
chicken and milk. Why? דאי סלקא דעתך דרבנן d'rabbanan. *de'i salka da'atach
derabbanan*, if you really think that it's only rabbinic, אכילה גופא achila
gufa גזירה gezeirah. *achila gufa gezeira*, the eating itself is a גזירה
gezeira *gezeira*, meaning eating them at the... not eating them cooked together,
but eating them at the table at the same time. You understand
how many degrees we've removed. First of all, they're not cooked together.
Eating really just a, you know, a cheeseburger... no, no, that's melted.
Eating, but let's say a sandwich which is like, you know, pastrami
and cheese, sandwich is דרבנן *derabbanan* because they're not cooked together. Okay,
so one level of rabbinic safeguard is even not cooked together. Now
we're adding another... now it's saying not only not cooked together, even
if you're... even if you're not eating them together, I can't be
eating at one table meat and you're eating milk. By the way,
the משנה Mishna *Mishna* speaks about cheese, not milk, because milk was
basically not used as a drink. It wasn't... oh, that might be
true, not pasteurized. Anyway, so anyway, but anyway, they would eat cheese.
So I can't eat at a table meat while Michael is eating
cheese because I might accidentally take some of his cheese, with some
certain exceptions that we'll see. So it's a double safeguard. They're not
cooked together, not only that, I'm not even eating both of them,
I'm just at the same table. So we're making all of these
safeguards. Rav says, would you really do that if chicken was just
דרבנן *derabbanan*? Okay, so eating them at the table itself is a
safeguard.
ואנא *va'ana* doesn't mean... doesn't mean just me by myself?
No, even we'll discuss... right, it means the simple case is maybe
by yourself, but we'll see it's talk to even somebody else under
most circumstances. Okay? ואנא גזרינן העלאה אטו אכילה *va'ana gazrinan ha'ala atu
achila*, and we're going to make a safeguard, don't put it on
the same table... I'm sorry, I misread the אכילה *achila* there. Okay,
I jumped ahead. אכילה *achila* there does mean eating together. It means
if the eating itself, eating of birds, excuse me, if the eating
itself of birds with milk is itself rabbinic, ואנא נגזור העלאה אטו
אכילה *va'ana nigzor ha'ala atu achila*, should we now go ahead and
prohibit even having it on the same table lest you come to
eat it together? נו *nu*, and if you came to eat it
together, big deal, it's only rabbinic, it's only birds. So how could
birds be rabbinic and then we're going to make yet another safeguard,
not only don't eat birds with milk, don't even have them on
the same table with milk. That's going a little too far. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ומאן תימא דלא גזרינן גזירה לגזירה gezeirah
le-gezeirah? *uman teima dela gazrinan gezeira ligezeira*, who told you we don't
make one safeguard on top of another? I'll tell you where we
do. Now, of course we're all familiar that very often the גמרא
*Gemara* says, how can you do this? You can't make one גזירה
gezeira, *gezeira* on top of another. So there's a little תוספות Tosfos,
*Tosafot* here, ומאן תימא *uman teima*, before we see the גמרא *Gemara*'s
answer דלא גזרינן גזירה לגזירה gezeirah le-gezeirah *dela gazrinan gezeira ligezeira*. תוספות
*Tosafot* says בכמה מקומות אמר היא גופא Gufa, גזירה gezeira, ואנן נקו
ונגזור גזירה לגזירה gezeira l'gezeira, *bechama mekomot amar hi gufa gezeira va'anan
neiku venigzor gezeira ligezeira*, sometimes the גמרא *Gemara* takes for granted that
we can't make one safeguard on top of another. And then he
gives you like five examples. Okay? And תוספות *Tosafot*'s last line says...
the last three lines, ויש בהרבה וכולי *veyesh beharbe vechulu*, אין לתמוה
גזירות gezeiros, חכמים זו לזו אלא במקום שהשעה מדמה *ein litmoha gzeirot
chachamim zu lezu ela bemakom shehasha medama*. Sometimes the גמרא *Gemara* takes
it for granted that we can't do it, sometimes the גמרא *Gemara*
says maybe we can maybe we can't, sometimes the גמרא *Gemara* makes
גזירה לגזירה gezeira l'gezeira *gezeira ligezeira* and doesn't even bat an eyelash,
and you can't... you know, the גמרא *Gemara* has a sense that
certain גזירות gezeiros *gezeirot* are different than others and either just don't
allow for doubling up or do allow or might allow and, you
know, you can't sort of... you can't figure out what the... what
standards the גמרא *Gemara*'s going to apply whether it... thinks that it
would be appropriate to make one case count on top of another.
But here the גמרא, rather than rather than accepting it without question
or rather than completely rejecting it, raises it, raises it as a
question. Are you allowed to make a גזירה לגזירה? How do you
why do you assume not? Maybe you can?
Right?
Doing the mental gymnastics and you just not.
But here it was here it was clear enough that there were
a lot of contradictions and he had no good resolutions, so yes,
that's true. Okay, doesn't even... right, doesn't even not even trying. Maybe
he tried but it was all off the page. Okay, anyway, so
it says, ומי נאמר דלא גזרינן גזירה לגזירה? u-mi nemar d'lo gazrinan
gezeirah le-gezeirah?
Who tells you you can't? It's תנן. Tnan. We taught in the
משנה. Mishna חלה... Challah...
I mean I will show you in a משנה Mishna that you
do make one safeguard on top of another. חלת חוצה לארץ נאכלת
עם הזר על
השולחן. Challat chutz la-aretz ne'echelet im ha-zar al ha-shulchan. Here's a very
similar and you understand what תוספות means about which things can you
compare. So this is very similar. I'm eating this חלה. challah. You
take חלה challah from you're making enough dough, you take it, you
give it to a כהן. Kohen. Outside of Israel, it's only רבנן
rabanan, because you're only because obviously the you know the it's only
for grain that's grown in the land of Israel. And not only
that, there's a double problem. Since we're all טמא, tamei, if it
were biblical and you were taking it, it would be טמא tamei
the כהן Kohen couldn't eat it. So the the stuff that you
eat out of the land of Israel, we're very lenient on. Number
one, it's רבנן, rabanan and number two, it's טמא tamei anyway. So
נאכלת עם הזר על השולחן, ne'echelet im ha-zar al ha-shulchan, the כהן
Kohen can eat it together with a non-כהן Kohen at the same
table, וניתנת לכל כהן שירצה, ve-nitenet le-chol Kohen she-yirtzeh, you can give
it to any כהן Kohen you want, and even a כהן Kohen
that's not so careful about laws of טומאה וטהרה. tumah ve-taharah. So
here you have a very similar case about eating at the same
table. Okay, I'm a כהן, Kohen, I'm eating my חלה. challah. I'm
afraid that Michael, a non-כהן, Kohen, he's sitting there, he might I
might accidentally or I might offer him a piece, I'll forget, he'll
take a piece of the חלה. challah. We're not concerned about that.
Why are we not concerned about that? Okay, because it would be
a double safeguard, right? The whole idea of חלת חוצה לארץ challat
chutz la-aretz is a safeguard to the idea of חלה, challah, an
extension of the idea of חלה. challah. To prohibit Michael to be
at the same table because he might accidentally take it, that would
be a safeguard on a safeguard, we don't make that גזירה. So
that's very similar, eating at the table for you might come to
eat, we don't we're not concerned about that for רבנן rabanan? issues.
So why would we be concerned about eating meat and milk at
the same table, chicken and milk, if that also is only רבנן?
Okay, so.
אמר ליה אביי. amar leh Abaye. So אביי Abaye said like this,
said back to
him. בשלמא אי אשמעינן חלת חוצה לארץ בארץ, bishlama i ashmeinan challat
chutz la-aretz be-aretz, if the case had been חלה challah from חוצה
לארץ chutz la-aretz that you were happened to be in the land
of Israel and you were eating this imported bread, דאיכא למיגזר משום
חלת ארץ, de-ika le-migzar mishum challat aretz, said that at least somewhere
in the offing was the eventual possibility it could come to eating
חלה challah from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael דאורייתא d'oraisa. which would be
biblical, ולא גזרינן, ve-lo gazrinan, and you would prove to me we
would not make a safeguard even though there was an eventual possibility
of a biblical transgression, איכא למשמע מינה, ika le-mishma minah, that would
be a good proof that we don't make one safeguard on top
of another. Okay, because because the but let me finish the sentence
and then we'll I'll I'll restate it'll be clear where he what
he's getting at. אלא חוצה לארץ, ela chutz la-aretz, you know why
we don't make the safeguard by חלה challah of חוצה לארץ? chutz
la-aretz? משום דליכא למיגזר הוא, mishum de-leika le-migzar hu, because it's not
even feasible, it's not even possible, meaning even if A leads to
B leads to C, if we're here in New York and I'm
eating חלת חוצה לארץ, challat chutz la-aretz, there's no way that in
the near future because I'm sitting at the table with Michael, he's
going to come to eat חלת ארץ ישראל challat Eretz Yisrael by
accident. Okay, it's not it's not in the offing because we didn't
live in a world with planes and you just jump on or
whatever. These were not things that were in the immediate realm of
possibility. So it's not just that it's not just we don't make
one safeguard on top of another, it's not we're going to bother
to make a safeguard if it's not even an eventual possibility in
any reasonable scope of activity. That's why, Michael, let's hold on, that's
why we don't do that, not because it's just a double safeguard.
אבל הכא, aval hacha, but here, דשרת ליה למיכל עוף וגבינה, de-sharat
leh lemichal of u-gevinah, if you let a person have meat and
cheese a excuse me chicken and cheese at the same table, אתי
למיכל בשר וגבינה, atei lemichal basar u-gevinah, he'll come to eat meat
he'll come to eat meat and cheese,
ומיכל בשר בחלב דאורייתא, u-michal basar be-chalav de-oraita, he'll come to eat
them both together. So it's saying as long as, meaning what is
the justification of a double safeguard in general? Meaning what's the reason
to say no and what's the justification yes? So the reason to
say no is that you know is that how many fences do
you need? You know, one thing should be enough to protect somebody
from transgressing. You know, one level, one boundary, one level of protection.
However, there are times where the slope is very slippery, and one
thing is not enough, and you you need a couple of protections
else somebody's going to very quickly slide in and A will lead
to B and oh this is good and that's good and that's
good. So the argument of why you can when you can make
a גזירה לגזירה is because you assess that it's very easy for
one thing to lead to the next to lead to the next.
And that's what the גמרא is saying. חלת חוצה לארץ Challat chutz
la-aretz nothing is going to lead anywhere, we're all here in New
York, nobody's about to eat חלת ארץ ישראל. challat Eretz Yisrael. But
if I have on my table chicken and cheese, then Michael's going
to go home or and he's going to have on his table.
so Rabbi Mizner had chicken and cheese, so he's going to put
down his hamburger and cheese. And if he puts down his hamburger
and cheese, next thing we know, his wife is going to eat,
sorry, Rivka, his wife. His wife is going to eat them together.
So one thing very easily slides into the next and therefore we
should make it, so it could be that oh, a lot of
hands, it could be that birds are rabbinic and even if birds
are rabbinic, we'll make a double safeguard because it's so easy for
one thing to slide into the next here. Yes, Michael.
But I don't understand, I mean if you stand, okay, when you
are both there in בבל, Bavel, people go from בבל Bavel there
to there all the time and I mean. Right. No, but they've
been in בבל Bavel always allowed to have חלה חוץ לארץ. Challah
Chutz La-aretz. Yeah.
It's true. Also there's a general question about גזירות, gezeiros which is
to what degree is the גזירה that this case will turn into
it or another case will turn into it. Now this does have
to be admittedly on, like one גזירה, don't read by a candle
light on שבת, Shabbos, you might tip the candle. There the concern
is that this case itself will be the transgression. Another case is
obviously not this case itself but some other similar case. And next
time it won't be chicken and cheese, next time it will be
meat and cheese. But even so, those are all, you're right, eventually
maybe I'll remember when I go to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael what
I used to do, blah blah blah, but it's certainly not the
sense of like it's in what I would call in the offing,
okay? Is it possible? Yes, it's not in the offing and therefore
the גמרא feels safe to bracket that. Charlie.
חלה Challah of the land of Israel, is that apply to bread
that was baked in land of Israel or bread from flour that
was.
Oh, what a good question.
It's been a while since I חזרתי chazered חלה Challah but if
I remember, it's actually baked that was bread that was both, flour
that was grown and kneaded in the land of Israel. Not necessarily
baked, but the kneading is what mattered.
And so that's going to be really rare.
Yeah. Right.
Yes, Rivka, I'm getting. To me the rabbis seem shameful of the
average person who is expected to understand all the degrees of ritual
purity and we went through them, so complicated, and yet not, not
be able to distinguish between chicken and meat. That they're going to
mix up if you're, if you, I don't understand that. Why would
they not trust people to know the difference?
Well, I do want to say something about this issue that comes
up about גזירות not trusting.
If someone, they didn't trust somebody in the sense of trust like,
like we don't think you're going to do the right thing, then
that's not what גזירות are made for. Somebody who's going to consciously
choose not to do the right thing was not going to care
about the גזירה, they were going to do the wrong thing anyway.
So it's a question about well-intentioned people that will do, will naturally,
you know, come to, to make mistakes or to confuse cases and
so that's the issue. I don't know if you would sort of
call it not trusting in the same way. That's number one. But
number two is, is that you know, I don't know. I mean
I think that it's very, I think it's realistic. I think if
you ask, as I said before, ask most people nowadays, you know,
or you tell somebody that you know, chicken and milk, chicken and
milk is only rabbinic, it's not biblical, maybe a lot of people
say of course, but I think there's a lot of people that
keep meat and milk and have no idea that that's only rabbinic
because we conceptualize it as meat. We don't think about the verse
of kid-goat in the mother's milk.
No, I'm asking, but they're saying if you, if you
allow fish and, and meat and people, I mean fish and cheese
and they will, the chicken and chicken
is what they're.
No no no no no no no no no no, not fish.
Chicken. Chicken, but they if you allow chicken and cheese, then you'll
allow meat, you'll allow like.
Why can't people understand that chicken is one thing and meat is
another?
Because I just said to you, do you think if you ask
10 people who keep meat and milk, right.
Whether it's rabbinic, but if you.
But that's what you have to understand, meaning if you, if you
don't understand that it's rabbinic, then you won't see why should it
matter if I'm, if I'm allowed to have and I saw Rabbi
Mizner had in his house chicken and cheese on the same table,
why should I not be allowed to have meat and cheese? And
the only thing that might make you think it's different is if
you're aware that one is rabbinic and one is דאורייתא.
Rivka's question was more, I think, of like why is chicken rabbinic
in the first place?
No, no, that's not her question.
Like chicken is different.
Fish is different, and they say people will not be able to
distinguish. If you allow chicken, then they'll assume meat is allowed. But
why can't they distinguish?
Meaning why can't you tell them, forget the reason, here's the point
guys, Rivka is
asking why you can't tell the difference between.
No, no, that's not what she's asking. No no. People, they're saying
people will distinguish between fish. You can allow, we're not worried that
they'll assume fish equals chicken.
But we're
worried they'll assume chicken equals.
Look, I think it makes a lot of sense.
I think it makes a lot of sense. People don't consider fish
to be a type of meat, although I will tell you, you
know, my kids go to a special needs school, so they're, they're
very sensitive to these כשרות kashrus issues, you know, because we tell
them all the things, so we tell them you know, no, you
know, you know, on a day that they're having meat they can't,
you can't give them milk. So we get an email from them:
Your son brought in a tuna fish sandwich. I just wanted to
check if this is considered meat or not.
So you see that was a ממה נפשך. mima nafshach. Anyway, most
people.
This is so on the other end of the practicality. I love
your question but what my thought is that it isn't even about
adults.
You put for example chicken and cheese on the table and your
little pish-hero comes along and grabs a little piece of chicken and
grabs a little piece of cheese and doesn't understand anything. So right
away there's a transgression. It's not that the kid's so little you
know but it's the idea that there's a violation right away so
that you don't do that, you don't do that.
It could be although you know if people like under בר מצוה
Bar Mitzva I don't see the גמרא generally concerned with that as
its population that it's making גזרות Gezeirot for.
But I'm just saying it's there and then they can make...
I think that's the point. Anything that becomes a general practice and
at the home you don't control the situations and things easily flow
one way.
But you don't want to go back to רי"ף. Rif.
Okay, yes okay last comment on this go ahead.
רי"ף Rif is absolutely right. The bottom line is we're supposed to
understand all these esoteric in order to run a house, in order
to live properly.
Wait, I have an answer to that.
Wait, I have a question.
And yet and what you can't believe and you can't tell us
this distinction
and the reason that we're talking this way is because we have
now considered for all these years chicken is meat. But if from
the very beginning, and I understood the reason about chicken is we
shouldn't be eating with the non-Jews, and so chicken was inexpensive compared
to meat and it was a more likely thing
to be eating with them that I don't know.
It used to
be much more expensive.
All right I actually have an...
go ahead Charlie.
You talk about complicated הלכות. halachot. All through ש"ס Shas we have
the issue of the חבר chaver versus the עם הארץ am ha'aretz
and it's not an ignorant person but someone who wasn't careful about
tithes and also about טומאה וטהרה. tuma and tahara. So yes so
a lot of people who were otherwise observant Jews didn't observe all
those complicated הלכות. halachot. Right so see how that turned out.
There were so many more complicated detailed הלכות halachot that people that
the Rabbis have to trust people what they're going to do in
their kitchen and you can't have a Rabbi...
but maybe that's Charlie's point which is that if you simplify and
this is unfortunate. This is what I tell my students is often
the אשכנזי Ashkenazi way of you know we had this before versus
the ספרדי. Sefardi. The אשכנזי Ashkenazi basically say what I call KISS:
keep it simple stupid. Okay we're going to make we're going to
flatten the distinctions and we're going to have rules which makes it
leads to more stringencies when you flatten distinctions it leads to more
stringencies but it also makes it easier to keep. You don't have
to worry about all the nuance. So if tithes were very difficult
for people to keep maybe people wanted to keep meat and milk
and we wanted to make it easy for people and simplify all
of the distinctions. Okay it's just a painful example of fish and
cheese. All right we have to move on, yes.
So one thing is you know and maybe this general thing like
you know sometimes we're saying oh we'll just publicize it you know
what I mean like we see that in the גמרא sometimes you
have to post something sometimes you're not so I'm trying to understand
why we can't publicize it. And the other thing is wait is
you know why I mean to me it seems that maybe because
we've been doing דף יומי Daf Yomi but you know just some
things you can put on the מזבח mizbe'ach some things you can't.
I can't put a chicken on the מזבח mizbe'ach
so
I would naturally think
it's different you know what
I mean maybe different laws.
Oh I can't do this with it I can't do that with
it okay so I can have it with milk because it's like
a different thing. I understand. Everyone knows all these distinctions because there's
no mother's milk. Right exactly so I don't see why we think
that people would get confused you know like I understand a cow
I can put on the מזבח mizbe'ach I can't bring my chicken
there everyone knows that people aren't going to say that like oh
you know what I can't put a cow so I'm gonna bring
a chicken instead. All right.
All
right I have no answer we're moving on. Everybody I gave you
all opportunity to voice your objection we're moving on. Okay fine all
right anyway we're moving on. All right so that's אביי's Abaye point.
אביי's Abaye point is yes it could be rabbinic but it's a
very slippery slope and we're going to make a safeguard. So and
it can be rabbinic. מתקיף ליה רב ששת Maskif leh Rav Sheshet
or ששת Sheshet asked on this סוף סוף צונן בצונן הוא. sof
sof tzon u-mitzon hu. I don't get it he said even if
whether even if you want to say bird is biblical certainly if
you want to say it's rabbinic there's no biblical transgression here because
it's all cold. It's your chicken together with your cheese. So what
type of need for a safeguard anyway? In this setting you're never
even if you have steak and cheese at the table you're never
going to transgress something biblical at this setting okay and to say
that you'll come next time to put them both in your mouth
okay that is not going to be biblical it's all cold. So
how is it going to lead from oh because I have it
at the table together now I'm going to cook it together? That's
not a logical flow. A logical flow is if I have chicken
I'll have meat. If I have meat at the table at the
same time next time I'll eat them together. Those are logical but
not that I'm going to consciously cook them together okay? So let's
take a look. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says no it
is a
possibility. גזירה שמא יעלה באילפס רותח. Gezeira shema ya'aleh be-ilfistirot. Oh yeah,
in them. Well, we'll see. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says סוף סוף כלי שני הוא וכלי שני אינו מבשל
*sof sof
kli sheni hu v'kli sheni eino mevashel*.
Nevertheless,
the stew pot is the second pot. It wasn't the pot from
the stove. You put it into some stew pot and you brought
it out. And anything in a second pot can't cook. So even
if you put cheese in it, it won't cook and it won't
become בשר בחלב *basar b'chalav*. So how will it ever lead to
it? אלא גזירה שמא יעלה בכלי ראשון *ela gezeirah shema ya'aleh bikli
rishon*. No, sometimes you bring straight the pot from the stove straight
to the table. So if you let people have them at the
table at the same time, it could lead, it won't lead to
a person consciously in their chicken... in their kitchen, you know,
making some type of meat-milk dish. But it will lead to one
time there'll be a boiling hot pot of stuff at the table
itself and you'll dip the... and you'll drop the cheese in because
it'll be right there, you'll forget. Oh, a little cheese will taste
some nice with this soup. And next thing you know, you're eating...
you're eating בשר בחלב דאורייתא *basar b'chalav d'oraisa*. So yes, it is
possible. Now you're saying maybe a little far-fetched, but it is possible
one could lead to the next. Yes, Charlie.
So if a כלי שני *kli sheni* can't cook, why do some
פוסקים *poskim* even object to a כלי שלישי *kli shlishi* by שבת
*Shabbos*?
So there's a question about whether you have the same definitions by
שבת *Shabbos* as by כשרות *Kashrus*. And by and large, we are
much more... although logically we should be more strict by כשרות *Kashrus*
because of the following reason: conceptually by שבת *Shabbos*, it's a definition
of cooking as a מלאכה *melacha* and that focuses much more on
process. And therefore you could say the classic cooking is something that
takes place in a כלי ראשון kli rishon *kli rishon* or even
on a fire, whereas
in a second or one degree removed vessel is not a classic
act of cooking. By כשרות *Kashrus*, the much bigger concern is not
process but result. Do the tastes get intermingled at the end result?
And therefore if they're both hot, they do. Absolutely. So logically you
should say by כשרות *Kashrus*, it's all about heat, and by שבת
*Shabbos* you need it to be in a כלי ראשון kli rishon,
*kli rishon*, that's more classic cooking. You are completely correct logically. However,
because of stringency, because שבת *Shabbos* is so much weightier, people are
much more careful about שבת *Shabbos* and say, well, maybe the vessel
doesn't matter, maybe heat is enough and so on, which leads to
stringencies beyond כלי ראשון kli rishon *kli rishon*. There's a degree question
of what degree of stringency we're talking about and what types of
cases... we're not talking about שבת *Shabbos* now, won't go into it.
But I'm going to answer your question. However, by כשרות *Kashrus*, because
it is true that there are biblical concerns, meat and milk or
whatever, but it's not שבת *Shabbos*. Therefore, we're more willing to take
the גמרא *Gemara*'s lead here where it emphasizes only כלי ראשון *kli
rishon* and draw the line there. Which is not to say that
sometimes there aren't concerns about כלי שני *kli sheni*, but yes, we're
much more willing to focus on כלי ראשון *kli rishon* by כשרות
*Kashrus*. So conceptually, yes exactly, conceptually you are correct
but that is how the הלכה halacha. *halacha* develops is the reverse
based on the degree of stringency. You have a question, Seth? I
don't understand the thing about the אילפיס רותח *ilpis roteach*. Was this
kind of a cultural thing, this is how they ate food?
Like they brought a boiling pot to the table and put things
in it? Because otherwise that seems like a little arbitrary. Well, you
mean the question that they brought it straight from the... straight from
the stovetop? Well, it just says... well, the גמרא *Gemara* considers that
it's like its second answer. Meaning no, obviously clearly they would first
bring it in a serving pot. But you know, every now and
then you're having a home meal, you know, whatever, you just bring
the pot straight... To save on glassware? Right, so right. I mean,
it's not saying it was classic. At first it assumed it was
a second pot. Then because it was in a corner, it said
oh, maybe sometimes you'll bring the actual, you know, pot from the
stove itself. Okay, you know, if it's one of those nights where
you don't have the effort, you just take it straight and you
put it on, exactly. All right, let's take a look now at
the next משנה Mishna, *Mishnah*. Ha, I thought we were going to
get a little caught up today. Food just goes through... next משנה
mishnah *Mishnah*: עוף עולה עם הגבינה על השולחן *of oleh im hagvinah
al hashulchan*. When it's when it's relevant, you know, that's when the
questions all come out. עוף עולה עם הגבינה על השולחן *of oleh
im hagvinah al hashulchan*. Here is now where... here's going back to
what we said which... what we said before but now showing it's
debated, which, by the way, points to
the fact that birds actually are rabbinic because we'll see that the
issue about birds with cheese is actually debated
between בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beis Shammai* and בית הלל Beis Hillel
*Beis Hillel*. עוף עולה עם הגבינה על השולחן *of oleh im hagvinah
al hashulchan*. Birds go with cheese... can go with cheese on the
table, ואינו נאכל *v'eino ne'echal*, but obviously can't be eaten... well, not
so obvious if it's rabbinic, but can't be eaten together. דברי בית
שמאי Beis Shammai *divrei Beis Shammai*. Here's בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beis
Shammai*'s going to be lenient. ובית הלל אומרים *u'Beis Hillel omrim*, בית
הלל Beis Hillel? *Beis Hillel* says לא עולה ולא נאכל *lo oleh
v'lo ne'echal*, the same way it can't be eaten you can't even
have it at the table at the same time. By the way,
the presence of this debate seems to indicate that it is rabbinic,
which is why we're debating it and we're not debating other types
of meat. אמר רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei *amar Rabbi Yosi*, said רבי
יוסי Rebbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi*, זו מקולי בית שמאי Beis Shammai ומחומרי
בית הלל Beis Hillel, *zu mikulei Beis Shammai u'mechumrei Beis Hillel*. This
is a leniency of בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beis Shammai* and a
stringency of בית הלל Beis Hillel *Beis Hillel*, which the גמרא *Gemara*'s
going to tell you isn't that pretty obvious. באיזה שולחן אמרו *be'eizeh
shulchan amru*, what type of table were they talking about? בשולחן שאוכל
עליו *beshulchan she'ochel alav*, on the table you eat on. אבל בשולחן
שסודר עליו את התבשיל *aval beshulchan shesoder alav es hatavshil*, but the
table that you actually are arranging, like you know, the buffet, right,
the counter... So in that type of a table, נותן זה בצד
זה ואינו חושש. You can have one next to the other and
not be concerned. Now that's a little bizarre because that's obviously where
the stuff is going to be in a כלי ראשון and boiling
hot and it's much more biblical concern and what do you mean
that you're not concerned? So רשי Rashi says, well yes, but it's
not like the concern is that in the middle of eating you
know you're talking and you're getting involved in conversation and your mind
is wandering and you're not paying attention and anything that's on the
table you'll go to come to eat and put together. Whereas if
you're very being conscious and getting the stuff ready to bring out
to the table, you're not sitting and actually eating there, you're not
going to while you're arranging it say, oh here's some cheese let
me put it into this pot. Okay so it's not the same
scenario of sort of of not paying attention and wandering and putting
things together at the table. Now that's what רשי Rashi says. I
would like to suggest a different explanation which is also based on
a רשי, the רשי we just read that said why we make
גזירה לגזירה, I didn't read the רשי inside but the רשי that
said why we make גזירה לגזירה because having them at the table
comes to eat, רשי has a nice phrase there which is which
is basically like העלאה זו אכילה. ha'ala'ah zo achila. Okay, putting on
the table that is eating. Now it could just mean it easily
becomes eating but I can think it also can mean a question
about a rabbinic definition. Because not everything, even if the point is
a safeguard, is not phrased as this is a safeguard, don't do
this it'll come to this. Some things are phrased as what I
would just call extensions, meaning when we say don't eat meat, don't
eat chicken, are we saying because if you eat chicken you'll come
to eat meat and we'll define it as a safeguard, that's one
way. But another way of saying it is no, we're going to
conceptualize at least at a rabbinic level the prohibition to be meat
and milk, not you know kid goat and milk or whatever. And
therefore we're going to define this as part of meat. Yes maybe
its purpose might be a safeguard but we're framing it as as
an as part of the definition as an extension of meat. Similarly
the whole issue right about why we go so crazy and we're
about to do the גמרא about the waiting period and having it
at the table, eating together, dot dot dot dot dot, that I
would argue is not just an issue of safeguards because then it
is, it's crazy, one safeguard after another. Don't eat don't even don't
even eat it within six hours you might come to have it
on the table you might come to eat it together like a
long list of things till you get to cooking them together, right,
or eating them cooked together. But what it might be is a
rabbinic redefinition of what does it mean to eat eat meat and
milk. To eat meat and milk might mean not only to put
them both in your mouth at the same time, that's one extension
of it even if they're not cooked together, okay that's by the
way the and being redefined, and meaning not cooked together but just
physically present. But it might but it might also mean not just
putting them in your mouth, having them at the same table is
eating meat and milk. Because I'm eating meat and the milk is
at the table, I'm eating meat and milk together. Not only that,
eating meat and milk when you have just put meat in your
mouth and a half hour later you're putting milk in your mouth
is also because the taste of the meat is still there and
all that, that's also a type of eating meat and milk together.
So what I would argue is is that the logic of these
extensions is that we're redefining what does meat mean, we're redefining what
does it mean to eat them together and so on. And that
explains, if I'm correct, that explains why we make a difference between
the table you're eating at and the table that you are setting
up the food. Because although the table you're setting up the food
is more likely, ironically, to lead to the biblical prohibition, right, because
you'll come and you know you'll drop one they're boiling hot right
there, but what we're doing is we're not just making safeguards. We're
saying the problem is eating them together, there you're not eating. But
if they're at the same table and you've got meat and milk,
that's considered eating together. That's how I understand what is going on
here. It explains a couple of other things in הלכה. halacha, Okay,
two quick questions. Okay, if this was a buffet okay, as I
like to call it. That would be different. That would be because
a groaning board. Right, so you're coming over to this table that
has these items. I assume a buffet would be the same issue
as the table you're eating at. Yeah yeah I assume a buffet
would be the same issue as as the table you're eating at.
Okay yeah and this is like a הלכתי halachic question. So I'm
trying to understand, when we say cooking meat and milk together we
mean like like this actual biblical... I understand like in a pot,
like you know you're making a soup. But let's say I take,
conceptually I'm trying to understand this is part of the same idea,
let's say I take I don't know my meat then I heat
up in the microwave some cheese and I pour on, is that
also considered cooking? Yes, so maybe maybe not, but that's not for
now. Okay we'll get to that later. Okay, the simple definition of
cooking like the גמרא said is כלי ראשון, it's on the it's
actually on a fire, it's cooking on the fire. Maybe if it's
a כלי ראשון that was taken off the fire and it's still
boiling hot. So what you're asking is the microwave cooking, that's a
separate conversation. לכל הפחות. l'chol hapachos. Yeah that's also a separate conversation.
עירוי iruy etc. Okay. Now let's take a look at the גמרא.
רבי יוסי היינו תנא קמא. Rabbi Yosei hainu Tanna Kamma. רבי יוסי
Rebbi Yossi says that this stringency of בית הלל Beit Hillel that's
exactly what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said, he didn't change anything.
וכי תימא אכילה גופא איכא בינייהו, V'chi teima achila gufah ika beiniyahu,
maybe they're discussing whether you can even eat them together. דקאמר תנא
קמא בהעלאה קא מיפלגי. D'ka'amar Tanna Kamma b'ha'ala'ah ka miflagi. מיפלגי meefligi
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma. is saying that they debate whether you
can have them on the same table, chicken and chicken and cheese,
ואכילה לא פליגי, ve-achila lo pligi, they agree you can't eat them
together. ואמרי רבי יוסי V'amrei Rebbi Yossi and maybe רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yossi is saying back, no, אכילה גופא מקולי בית שמאי וחומרי בית
הלל, mikulei Beis Shammai u-chumrei Beis Hillel, maybe he's saying back that
even eating is debated about בית שמאי Beit Shammai. and בית הלל?
בית שמאי Beis Hillel Beis Shammai, even lets you eat chicken and
cheese together? You can't say that, ותניא ve-tanya or it should be
ותנן ve-tnan we taught in a משנה in עדיות, Eduyos, רבי יוסי
אומר ששה דברים מקולי בית שמאי ומחומרי בית הלל, Rebbi Yossi omer
shisha d'varim mikulei Beis Shammai u-michumrei Beis Hillel, six things are from
the leniencies of בית שמאי Beit Shammai, and the stringencies of בית
הלל, Beit Hillel וזו אחת מהן, ve-zu achas meihen, this is one
of them, עוף עולה עם גבינה על השולחן ואינו נאכל דברי בית
שמאי, Of oleh im gevina al ha-shulchan ve-eino ne'echal divrei Beis Shammai,
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says it goes on the table and can't
be eaten, ובית הלל אומרים לא עולה ולא נאכל, u-Veis Hillel omrim
lo oleh ve-lo ne'echal, not only can it not be eaten, it
can't go on the same table. Exactly the language of the תנא
קמא. Tanna Kamma, So what is רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi say, he's
saying exactly the תנא קמא, so why did the משנה after saying
רבי יוסי's Rebbi Yossi quote then have רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi say
it again? So the גמרא says, אלא הא קמשמע לן, ela ha
kamashma lan, מאן תנא קמא רבי יוסי, man Tanna Kamma Rebbi Yossi,
you're right, רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi. isn't adding anything. The משנה's just
saying here's the ruling, be aware this is what we learned רבי
יוסי was the one that taught us this. Why is it saying
that? כל האומר דבר בשם אומרו מביא גאולה לעולם, kol ha-omer davar
beshem omro meivi geula la-olam, and now we have a nice line
the גמרא quotes every now and then, to tell you the importance
which is of course central to the entire rabbinic tradition, that you
quote everybody, you know, you attribute statements to who was the original
person who said it, because whoever says something in the name of
the one who said it will eventually causes redemption to be brought
to the world. שנאמר, shene'emar, as the verse says, ותאמר אסתר למלך
בשם מרדכי, va-tomer Esther la-melech beshem Mordechai, right? Esther told the king
what מרדכי Mordechai had said about בגתן ותרש, Bigtan ve-Teresh, בגתן Bigtan
and תרש, Teresh, and ultimately that led to the king remembering מרדכי
Mordechai and redemption came, so if you give things their proper attribution.
It's quite interesting, like I said, it's the staple of the rabbinic
tradition, בשם, beshem, you know, so-and-so said in the name of so-and-so,
in the name of so-and-so, in the name of so-and-so, but what
is interesting is that in the משנה, because of רבי's sort of
agenda of creating, you know, of having a סתם stam rulings of
the משנה, actually it wasn't all just רבי, there was a lot
of סתם משנהs stam Mishnah that existed pre-רבי, but the גמרא sometimes
makes it very clear that רבי chose to make certain statements סתם,
stam, anonymous, in order that they would become weighty and then that
they would sort of be treated as the accepted הלכה, halacha as
as law, that required sometimes dropping who was the one that actually
said it to give it the greater weight. So here what the
גמרא's actually saying is that it was a סתם משנה, stam Mishnah,
but because of this value, here at least רבי went ahead and
gave it the right attribution to רבי יוסי. It would also have
been possible to say that because it is very rare that בית
הלל בית שמאי, Beis Hillel Beis Shammai did the battery run out?
Maybe. Oh well, okay. Because it's very rare the debate of בית
הלל בית שמאי Beis Hillel Beis Shammai that בית שמאי Beit Shammai
is lenient and בית הלל Beit Hillel is strict, maybe you just
have to, you want to emphasize when it's the case so you
don't say oh that must have been a mistake and correct it
to to reverse it. Anyway, that's why we have the בית הלל
Beit Hillel בית שמאי Beit Shammai? case over there. Okay, so now
the גמרא goes on, there's a lot more, yeah. Okay, so now,
תנא אגרא, Tana Igra, now we get to the motherlode as it
would be, of the discussion of the waiting period between meat and
milk, because we had just spoken about not eating them at the
same table, so not eating at the same table is going to
lead to the issue of the waiting period, and again, if you
just look at this as a safeguard, it seems very far-fetched, but
conceptually I understand this to be as I said, a definition of
what does it mean to eat together. So let's take a look.
תנא אגרא חמוה דרבי אבא, Tana Igra chamu-ei de-Rebbi Abba, so אגרא
Igra the father-in-law of רבי אבא Rebbi Abba taught, עוף וגבינה נאכלין
באפיקורן, Of ve-gevina ne'echalin be-afikoren, bird and cheese are eaten with הפקר,
hefker, okay, more or less, meaning like you don't have to be
careful about the order of eating meat and milk, of eating cheese
and bird. Now the משנה says they can't be at the same
table. So this is like a comment on that. Yes, they can't
be at the same table, but if they're not at the same
table, it doesn't really matter if you eat them right after one
another. That's how it's eventually going to be translated. הוא תני לה
והוא אמר לה, Hu tana lah ve-hu amar lah, he taught this
ברייתא, baraita. you know, which he went tradition, taught as a tradition,
and then he himself offered the commentary on it. בלא נטילת ידים
ובלא קינוח הפה. Belo netilas yadayim u-velo kinuach ha-peh. You don't have
to wash your hands and you don't have to wipe out your
mouth. Okay, so as you may know, technically speaking, after you eat
cheese, מילכיגס Milchigs cheese, the hard cheese discussion will, I'll mention to
you later. After you eat מילכיגס Milchigs cheese or whatever, you can
basically have meat right afterwards. Most people, I don't know, at least
a lot of people wait a half hour, but really the הלכה
halacha is, and if you, you know, there's no problem in doing
this, if you make sure that there's nothing on your hands, you
wipe out your hands, you clean out your mouth, you eat something
in between, maybe you drink something, we'll talk about that in a
minute, you can go ahead and eat meat right afterwards. And the
purpose is, if you have stuff still on your hands or in
some taste in your mouth, it'll mix with the meat and it'll
be like again, eating them together. But if you make sure that
that's off, out of your hands and your mouth, then there's no
problem about eating them together. He comes along and he says that
oh by the way, by birds and cheese you don't even have
to worry about that. That would presumably be by meat... And cheese,
again indicating that birds are more lenient, they're דרבנן. So while we
might be strict about not having them on the table at the
same time, if you eat them one after the other, you don't
even have to worry about washing your hands and cleaning out your
mouth. Not so clear either way. For now we'll assume that it
means cheese first and then the meat. Okay? That's the תוספות, a
big debate. For now we'll assume the easier case. Okay? That because
it's presumably because it's only rabbinic, you don't have to worry about
doing anything and right after one right after the other you can
eat even though they can't be at the table at the same
time. Okay? רבי יצחק בריה דרב משרישיא, Rebbi Yitzchak brei d'Rav Mesharshiya,
now we're going to have a story. רבי יצחק Rebbi Yitzchak the
son of רב משרישיא, Rav Mesharshiya, איקלע לבי רב אשי. ikla l'bei
Rav Ashi. He chanced he came to visit the house of רב
אשי. אייתו ליה גבינה אכל. ayitei lei gvina achal. They brought him
some cheese and he ate it. אייתו ליה בישרא אכל. ayitei lei
bisra achal. They brought him some meat, presumably some you know בשר
בהמה, basar beheima, like a steak or whatever, and he ate it.
ולא משי ידיה, v'lo mashi yadei, he did not wipe his hands.
אמרו ליה, amrei lei, they said to him, והתניא איגרא חמוה דרבי
אבא עוף וגבינה נאכלין באפיקורן. v'ha-tanya Igra chamu d'Rebbi Abba of u-gvina
ne'echalin b'afikoren. But didn't we teach a ברייתא baraita that chicken and
cheese can be eaten with like, you know, with הפקר hefker like
without any distinction? עוף וגבינה, of u-gvinin, but that's only birds and
cheese, because birds are rabbinic presumably is the subtext here. בשר גבינה
לא, basar gvina lo, not real meat, you know, real red meat,
that you would need to do some distinction. אמר להו, amar lehu,
הני מילי בליליא, hani mili b'leilya, that's at night. אבל ביממה הא
קחזינא. aval b'yimama ha kachazina. But at day I can look at
my hands. I saw that my hands were clean. I don't have
to wash my hands. What about the mouth? My kids try that
on me. What? Wash your hands? They look fine! So anyway, I
looked at my hands. So what about his mouth? So we'll see
in a minute. It might be it's either or. Or if it
were an issue about mouth, maybe he ate something between it. They
were sitting at the meal. He ate some bread. He drank something.
That might have been considered cleaning out the mouth, but they said
he didn't do anything with his hand. So I don't have to
worry about that. Okay, so now what we are seeing is is
that you can eat chicken after cheese, and we'll assume again now
that the milk is first. Okay? Talk about that more tomorrow. Chicken
after cheese or meat after cheese as long as you clean off
your hands and wipe out your mouth and by chicken actually because
it's only rabbinic you don't even merely even have to do that.
You can do it right afterwards. Okay. Let's keep on going. תניא,
tanya, we taught a ברייתא. baraita בית שמאי אומרים מקנח ובית הלל
אומרים מדיח. Beit Shammai omrim mekane'ach u'Beit Hillel omrim medi'ach. So this
presumably now this is quite interesting because again you know in our
משנה we only had the... there is clearly is a development. The
whole idea of the waiting of the of the time and the
six hours that's clearly at the Amoraic period. The middle stage of
the development seems to be like the משנה only speaks about not
being at the same table. In the גמרא you get the idea
about cleaning out the hands and so on. In the משנה you
don't have that. Maybe in the משנה one right after the other,
no discussion. But here though it's a little bit seems that you
know on the one hand you had this איגרא Igra teaching a
ברייתא that spoke about it, but now you actually have another ברייתא
that's putting this all the way back to בית הלל Beit Hillel
and בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So it's interesting it's not in our
משנה, but here it does seem to be, although they're not explicitly
talking about our case about about meat and milk, but that's the
way the גמרא understands it, that even בית הלל Beit Hillel. בית
שמאי, Beit Shammai. the same ones that were debating being at the
table the same time, were also discussing some need of division between
eating one right after the other. Still though the idea of waiting
six hours, waiting time, it'll be on tomorrow's דף, daf, or actually
what today's דף daf is, anyway that is that comes later. So
let's take a look. בית שמאי אומרים מקנח ובית הלל אומרים מדיח.
Beit Shammai omrim mekane'ach u'Beit Hillel omrim medi'ach. בית שמאי Beit Shammai
says wipe out your mouth, and בית הלל Beit Hillel says rinse
out your mouth. מאי מקנח ומאי מדיח? mai mekane'ach u'mai medi'ach? What's
meant by this? Meaning to what degree are these excluding one another?
Top of ק"ו עמוד א, kof-vav amud aleph, today's real דף. daf.
אילימא בית שמאי אומרים מקנח ולא בעי מדיח ובית הלל אומרים מדיח
ולא בעי מקנח. iyleima Beit Shammai omrim mekane'ach v'lo ba'ei medi'ach u'Beit
Hillel omrim medi'ach v'lo ba'ei mekane'ach. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says that
you only wipe out your mouth and you don't need to rinse
out your mouth, and בית הלל Beit Hillel says the exact opposite,
just rinse it out, don't wipe it out, that one says this
is better and the other says that is better. אלא הא דאמר
רבי זירא אין קינוח פה אלא בפת. ela ha d'amar Rebbi Zeira
ein kinuach peh ela b'pat. But so if רבי זירא Rebbi Zeira
says the way you wipe out your mouth, like nobody said take
a napkin and wipe it out, right? So they mean wipe it
out with food. So when he said the way you do it
is with bread, כמאן? Who is that going like? בית שמאי? Beit
Shammai He wouldn't rule like בית שמאי. Beis Shammai We don't rule
like בית שמאי. Beis Shammai So if he is telling us the
proper way to wipe out the mouth, it must be that בית
הלל Beit Hillel, says that you not only rinse the mouth but
you also wipe it. So אלא, here's a way to read the
debate. בית שמאי אומרים מקנח ולא בעי מדיח. Beit Shammai omrim mekane'ach
v'lo ba'ei medi'ach. בית שמאי Beis Shammai says just wipe it out,
don't rinse it out. ובית הלל אומרים אף מדיח, u'Beit Hillel omrim
af medi'ach, you have to do both, wipe it and rinse it.
Which would explain why we're describing how you wipe it out. But
that can't be, דהוי ליה מקולי בית שמאי ומחומרי בית הלל, de-havei
lei mikulei Beit Shammai u'mechumrei Beit Hillel, then it would be a
leniency of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and a stringency of בית הלל.
Beit Hillel ולתני גבי קולי בית שמאי ומחומרי בית הלל, v'lisnei gabei
kulei Beit Shammai u'mechumrei Beit Hillel, should have been taught amongst that
list. It can't be בית שמאי saying either and בית הלל Beis
Hillel saying both because that would make בית הלל Beis Hillel strict.
אלא, so here's the problem. בית הלל, Beis Hillel because we have
a ruling about what it means to wipe out your mouth, we
have to make that part of בית הלל's Beis Hillel ruling. But
once... make it part of בית הלל's Beis Hillel ruling, how do
you do that and keep בית הלל Beis Hillel to be the
lenient position? So here's how you do it. אלא, בית שמאי אמרי
amri מקנח והוא הדין למדיח. mekaneach v'hu hadin l'madiach. It must be
that they're really not debating for once. They're just saying different things.
בית שמאי saying you can wipe it out, but it's true you
could also rinse it. ובית הלל אמרי מדיח והוא הדין למקנח. u'Beis
Hillel amri madiach v'hu hadin l'mekaneach. You can rinse rinse it, but
it's true you could also wipe it. מר מחדא ומר מחדא ולא
פליגי. mar machada u'mar machada v'lo pligi. Each one is saying one
option and they don't disagree. So you never need both. It's one
or the other. Now, of course, it's funny because you could have
kept בית הלל Beis Hillel, lenient by having בית הלל say an
or, meaning בית שמאי could have said only wipe it out, and
בית הלל could say you could also rinse it out. Yes, you
can wipe, but you can also rinse. That might have been an
easier way to read it, which would have had בית הלל more
lenient and would have had them arguing. It's funny the גמרא did
not pick that option. Anyway, that's our conclusion, and our conclusion is
that when you are having meat after cheese after milk, just we
said before, rinse your hands, and now we're saying do something with
your mouth, either wipe it out or rinse it out. Let's just
talk about how that process of wiping and rinsing. What bread? Well,
yes, yes, let's just see what that is. Okay. גופא, let's take
a look at that. אמר רב זירא אין קינוח הפה אלא בפת.
Amar Rav Zeira ein kinuach hapeh ella b'pas. You wipe out your
mouth with bread. והני מילי בדחטי. V'hani mili b'dichti. That's only by
wheat bread. אבל דשערי לא. Aval d'shari lo. Barley bread not, because
it crumbles and it doesn't do a good job wiping out the
mouth. ודחטי נמי לא אמרן. V'dichti nami lo amran. Wheat bread we
only say it אלא בקרירא ella b'karira if it's cold, because then
it's a little hard. אבל בחמימא Aval b'chamima if it's hot bread,
משתר שרי, mishtar shari, it also like sort of tears and crumbles
and does not do a good job at wiping out the mouth.
והני מילי ברכיכא V'hani mili b'rachicha if it's soft, אבל באקושה aval
b'akusha if it's hard bread, like really hard, then it'll break into
pieces. Cracker? No, it'll crack. Right, yes, that won't do a good
job. והלכתא, V'hilchasa, so while we have all those qualifications, the real
הלכה is בכל מילי הוי קינוח. b'chol mili havei kinuach. You can
use any type of food to wipe out your mouth, not just
bread, not just wheat bread, whatever. לבר, L'var, the only foods you
cannot consider to do a job of cleaning out your mouth are
קמחא kimcha flour, obviously, that won't do a good job, ותמרי, v'tamri,
oh there you go, dates, וירקא v'yarka and vegetables. Okay? Those types
of things are not. Just those? Presumably any other food would be
okay. Presumably. So now basically and we'll end with this today, our
משנה says don't have them at the same table. The way I
framed it is, yes, there's a concern you'll eat it together, but
we're conceptually calling that eating together. The גמרא introduced some תנאים Tannaim
and בית הלל, בית שמאי that says even one after the other
can't, but the most here that we've said until this point is
some type of wiping the hands, cleaning the mouth is enough, even
in the case of meat it might not even be needed by
chicken. We haven't really discussed whether order matters, but we'll discuss that
tomorrow. But until this point all of the scenarios have been where
the milk is first and the meat is second. We will talk
more about that tomorrow. Okay, גמר חתימה טובה gmar chasima tova everybody.
Goodbye.